<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of the proceedings of the late Parliament of England An. Dom. 1689, being the first in the reign of their present Majesties King William and Queen Mary.</title>
            <author>Somers, John Somers, Baron, 1651-1716.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60885</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4645</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12268</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11911632</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11911632</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50841</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60885)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50841)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 514:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of the proceedings of the late Parliament of England An. Dom. 1689, being the first in the reign of their present Majesties King William and Queen Mary.</title>
                  <author>Somers, John Somers, Baron, 1651-1716.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 25, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Dorman Newman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Somers.  Cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1]-[3] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50841:1"/>
            <p>A VINDICATION OF THE PROCEEDINGS OF THE Late Parliament, <hi>A.D.</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50841:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50841:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VINDICATION OF THE PROCEEDINGS OF THE <hi>Late Parliament</hi> OF ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1689.</p>
            <p>Being the Firſt in the Reign of Their preſent Majeſties King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Dorman Newman,</hi> at the <hi>King</hi>'s-<hi>Arms</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="vindication">
            <pb facs="tcp:50841:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50841:3"/>
            <head>A VINDICATION OF THE PROCEEDINGS OF THE <hi>Late Parliament</hi> OF ENGLAND.</head>
            <p n="1">I. THE Proceedings of the late Parliament were ſo fair, ſo prudent, ſo neceſſary, and ſo advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous to the Nation, to the Proteſtant Intereſt in general, and in particular to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that all true Engliſh-Men muſt needs acknowledge they owe to the then Repreſentatives of the Nation, their Privileges, their Liberties, their Lives, their Religion, their preſent and future ſecurity from Popery, Slavery, and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Power, had they done nothing elſe but enacted the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50841:4"/>Rights and Liberties of the Subject, and ſettling the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of the Crown.</p>
            <p>So that it is now, and perhaps but now, that we may call our ſelves the Free-born Subjects of <hi>England,</hi> as being fully ſecured, for ever, by this Act, from the heavy and inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable Yoke of Arbitrary Power, the neceſſary Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of a Power of diſpenſing, or ſuſpending of Laws, without conſent of Parliament.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Their ſettling the Crown upon the Head of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Prince, who is the very Centre, the chief Prop and Pillar of the Proteſtant Religion, ſecures all Proteſtants not only at home, but likewiſe in all other parts of <hi>Europe;</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that it is upon him only we ground all our Hopes of ſeeing, e'er long, <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. called to a juſt account for all his Unjuſt, Arbitrary, and Tyrannical Proceedings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his own Subjects, as likewiſe againſt his injured and weaker Neighbours.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Their not acting in the leaſt, after the example of their Neighbours, againſt Prelacy, but rather favouring it by ſuch Acts as fit only Epiſcopal Men for publick Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, gives all reaſonable ſatisfaction to the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> without any juſt offence, either given to the Diſſenters, who, under the preſent Government, enjoy, to their own Hearts deſire, their long wiſh'd for Liberty, without being liable to the laſh of the Law, for ſerving God after their own way: Notwithſtanding all this, ſo hard, yea, ſo impoſſible a thing it is to content all Parties; not a few vent their Malice in every Corner, yea, and in Print too, againſt the King and Parliament, though all their Proceedings hitherto tend ſo directly to the general good of the Nation, that we muſt either want common Underſtanding not to ſee it, or prove moſt ungrateful to our Repreſentatives not to acknowledge ſuch an evident truth as this is with our moſt thankful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns. To proceed with ſome method in this deſigned Vindication of the late Parliament, I ſhall, firſt, take a ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50841:4"/>view of the late condition of our Affairs; and, ſecondly, give a full anſwer to whatever is maliciouſly ſuggeſted to the unthinking Multitude; yea, and in Printed Pamphlets likewiſe, to the ſeducing of the ſimple, and to the great en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of the profeſſed Enemies and Diſturbers of the preſent Government.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. If we conſider in what condition we were in, the two laſt years of King <hi>James</hi>'s Reign, we may remember we were given up for loſt by all our Friends in <hi>Europe,</hi> and did think ſo to our ſelves, it being then impoſſible for us to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine from whence our relief ſhould come. A Power of diſpenſing with, and ſuſpending of Laws, and the execution of Laws, was already ſo fully eſtabliſhed, that the very humble petitioning to be excuſed from concurring to the ſaid aſſum'd Power, was Crime enough for the Commitment and Proſecution of divers worthy Prelates: The Court of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners for Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes was a ſort of Inquiſition; or, at leaſt, a certain Fore-runner of the new way of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting People, by the irreſiſtible Eloquence of arm'd Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons: The levying Money for, and to the uſe of the Crown, by pretence of Prerogative, for other time, and in other manner, than the ſame was granted by the Parliament, was nothing elſe but a preparatory contrivance, to try afterwards a French experiment upon the Gold and Silver of the Nation: The horrible and illegal Puniſhments inflicted by corrupt Judges, exceſſive Fines and Bails, and ſeveral Grants and Promiſes made of Fines and Forfeitures, before any Conviction or Judgment againſt the Perſons, upon whom the ſame were to be levyed; and all the other Injuſtices, Grievances, and Irregularities of thoſe days, were but previous diſpoſitions to the new modelling of the Nation into a Frame, the more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily to be wrought upon by the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Prieſts, in caſe their weak Arguments could not prevail, as 'twas impoſſible they ſhould have prevailed, in a Nation ſo well provided and ſtock'd with ſolid Learning, both againſt Error, and Superſtition.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:50841:5"/> V. If this was our condition within our ſelves, it was made much worſe by the diſmal proſpect of the threatning French Greatneſs: The French King's known and cloſe En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements with the late King <hi>James,</hi> the ſudden Growth of his Power, both by Sea and by Land, ſeem'd to threaten all his Neighbours with the utmoſt Deſolation, unleſs, by laying aſide the uſe of their Reaſon, they acted all like Fools, and turned Papiſts; which could not ſecure them neither from Oppreſſion and Slavery, ſince none are greater Slaves, nor ſo unmercifully oppreſſed as the French Papiſts themſelves: This is but a ſhort and ſummary view of the publick Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities and Miſeries we lay under, till our Deliverer came over to free us from them, by the beſt Methods our Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives could fall upon for our ſafety in times to come; which are certainly ſuch as give full ſatisfaction to all good Men, and Loyal Subjects, that are not ſtill in love with Popery and Slavery, both of Body and Soul, which always attends it: So that the preſent poſture of our Affairs is now ſuch, that we have all reaſon to hope, if we can but agree among our ſelves, this Kingdom may become again, as 'twas of old, the terrour of <hi>France. Europe</hi> never bid fairer for a level of the French Monarch, he being now ſurrounded on all ſides, by thoſe he has made his irreconcileable Enemies, by his daily breaches of Oaths, by his Oppreſſions and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſions, contrary to all Treaties made with him, either of Peace or Truce.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. We cannot then but highly commend the prudent meaſures of the laſt Parliament, for ſupplying his Majeſty with neceſſaries, towards a vigorous proſecution of this preſent War the Nation ſo long wiſh'd for in vain, the French Intereſt prevailing too much formerly at the Court of <hi>England,</hi> againſt the Intereſt of the Proteſtant Religion, and of the Engliſh Nation. Such then as complain of ſome preſent hardſhips, always unavoidable in time of War, and would fain work the People into a belief of a happier condition un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50841:5"/>another change of Affairs, ſeem not to underſtand their true Intereſt; for muſt we expoſe our ſelves to a certain ruine, to the loſs of our Lives and Liberties, by not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing liberally to the maintenance of a War, ſo neceſſary in this preſent juncture of our Affairs? Our <hi>All</hi> lies now at the Stake, our Lives, Properties, Liberties, and Religion: Should any <hi>Tax,</hi> or <hi>Impoſt,</hi> put us out of Humor, and cauſe us to wiſh for a change, as if we could pretend to any ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, in caſe things were ſettled again upon the ſame Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation they were on before?</p>
            <p n="7">VII. Are we not ſufficiently acquainted, from daily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, with this undoubted Popiſh Principle, <hi>That a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt is obliged to break his Oath taken not to extirpate Hereſie, as ſoon as he is in a capacity to root out what he thinks Hereſie, under a no leſs pain than that of Eternal Damnation?</hi> King <hi>Lewis</hi> has ſatisfied all the World, by what he has lately done, that this is no Calumny; and King <hi>James</hi> cleared all our Doubts upon the matter, by what he likewiſe really did, and endeavoured to doe.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. But a late Seditious Pamphlet tells us a Tragical Story of the decay and loſs of Trade by this preſent War, That <hi>the</hi> Dutch <hi>run away with our Trade at Sea, and the</hi> French <hi>with our Ships:</hi> This is but a meer groundleſs flouriſh, that can only make impreſſion upon ſome weak Minds, that neither underſtand their own Intereſt, nor that of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they are in; 'tis true, we have loſt ſeveral Ships, and that is unavoidable in the beginning of any War as well as in this, till the Merchant-Men bound homewards are informed of a War declared, which muſt needs require ſome time; but of late we have loſt none, or we have taken the equivalent of our loſſes from the Enemy; and for the time to come, his Majeſty has taken ſuch meaſures, that it ſhall not be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after in the Power of the French to put a ſtop to our Trade, either into <hi>Holland, Spain,</hi> the Eaſt Countries, or <hi>Weſt</hi> and <hi>Eaſt Indies;</hi> and as for the Dutch, 'tis a groundleſs ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50841:6"/>though too often in the Mouths of ſuch as are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected to the Government, <hi>That they run away with our Trade,</hi> ſince the contrary may be eaſily made out to an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prejudiced Mind; Do we not Trade ſtill, as well as the Dutch, both to the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> to <hi>Sweedland, Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark, Hamburgh,</hi> and <hi>Poland?</hi> Do the French allow them free paſſage more than to us? And if they ſend abroad greater Merchant Fleets, and perhaps under greater Convoys than we do; by ſo doing they rather lend us a helping Hand, than wrong us; becauſe in the mean time they clear the Seas of French Privateers, which makes of courſe our Voyages the ſafer, and great Convoys not ſo abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, as they would be at another time, when we were not in Union with the Dutch: So that ſuch reflexions are either but idle and frothy Diſcourſes, or made upon a deſign to raiſe Sedition, and ſtir up the Nation againſt the preſent Government: But grant that what this diſaffected Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phleteer ſays were really true, as it is not, in the full mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure he would have it, let us balance our preſent decay of Trade on the one ſide, and on the other hand the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of not proſecuting vigorouſly the preſent War againſt the French, and we ſhall eaſily diſcover either the groſs miſtakes of ſuch as diſcourſe after this rate, or their real deſigns to ruine their Country, by preferring a ſmall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniency of not ſo ſull a Trade, to the very being of Liberty and Religion, and perhaps of the Nation it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. For let us allow to this pretended Politician, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired change of Government he ſeems to aim at, this can never happen but in one of theſe three ways, either by the returning of King <hi>James</hi> again, or by the invaſion of King <hi>Lewis,</hi> or by a Civil War at home; which laſt thing, if ſome do really intend, they deſign nothing elſe but their own ruine, and that of their Country; and if they would have King <hi>James</hi> to come again, muſt he come in by Conqueſt? If he ever recovers <hi>England</hi> by Conqueſt, where are then
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50841:6"/>our Properties, our Liberties, our Religion, our Laws, and whatever Privileges we now glory in, and that no other Subjects in the World can boaſt of? Would they have King <hi>James</hi> come in again by agreement? Beſides, the apparent impoſſibility of the thing, upon ſeveral and obvious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, I would willingly be ſatisfied, as I was ſaying before, how we can truſt him after ſo many violations of his Word, and ſince by the Principles of his Religion, he is obliged in Conſcience not to keep either Word given, or Oath taken, to protect and promote Hereſie, if he is once in Power to deſtroy it. If our Pamphleteer pretends to a Change of Government, by a French Invaſion, he muſt either be a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed French Papiſt, or a very bad Engliſh Proteſtant, and quite of a different temper from all true Engliſh-Men, who have ſtood in oppoſition from all times to the French Intereſt, not only upon the account of the Proteſtant Religion, but likewiſe becauſe of their Civil Rights, which both they muſt of neceſſity part with, if the French ever got footing in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>X. I confeſs, as things now ſtand, there is little or no danger at all of their attempting the Conqueſt of their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Conquerors, the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> becauſe of our Union at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, againſt <hi>France</hi> with ſo many powerful Allies; but yet if we take not hold of this opportunity by the Fore-look, I know not what may happen in another Scene of Affairs, in caſe we were leſt alone to deal with the French, who by the connivance of the laſt two Reigns, are become ſo formidable at Sea, as to be a match either for Us, or the Hollanders. Now can any Man of reach blame the King for recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſo often to the late Parliament, the abſolute neceſſity of proſecuting vigorouſly the preſent War, in this preſent juncture of our Affairs; or find fault with the Repreſentatives of the Nation, for ſupplying him with the neceſſary Sinews of War; eſpecially, ſince he has offered to give them an Account of the diſpoſal of their Money for the very uſes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50841:7"/>they deſigned it for: Neither can we be jealous of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Deſign in calling in Foreigners, in order to the ſpeedy reduction of <hi>Ireland;</hi> becauſe 'tis a matter of great Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, for the Humbling of <hi>France</hi> both by Sea and by Land; together with our Allies, to put an end to our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick Broils, with all poſſible expedition; and this cannot be better performed, than by joining to our own Forces a Body of veterane and experienced Forreigners.</p>
            <p>XI. But this looks, ſay ſome of our Male-Contents, as if his Majeſty miſtruſted his own Subjects, which if narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly looked into, is a meer groundleſs aſperſion, ſince all his Majeſty's Forces both by Sea and by Land, an inconſiderable number of Foreigners excepted, are Natives, either of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland,</hi> or <hi>Ireland:</hi> Does the French King miſtruſt his own Subjects, becauſe of his joyning with them ſeveral Foreign Nations, as <hi>Switzers, Italians,</hi> and both <hi>Engliſh, Scotch,</hi> and <hi>Iriſh,</hi> upon occaſion; the true reaſon of this common Practice is, that an Army conſiſting of Forces of different Nations, is upon this account more formidable than it would be if it conſiſted of meer Natives, that both thoſe Foreigners, and the Natives, fighting through emulation, leave no ſtone unturned to out-doe one another; the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving of this Maxim made the Dutch a free People, to the pitch we ſee them in at this day: The French likewiſe owe in part their preſent Greatneſs to the valour of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, Scotch,</hi> and <hi>Switzers,</hi> who fighting not ſo much out of any particular kindneſs to them, as for their own reputation, were wont to overthrow whatever ſtood in their way, to the great advantange of the French, under whoſe pay they then were; undoubtedly this is his Majeſty's deſign in ſending for Foreigners, that the Natives may act their parts the better by Emulation and Example: So that though it be allowed to be true, as certainly it is, that King <hi>William</hi> has a ſufficient number of his own Subjects to reduce <hi>Ireland,</hi> and thoſe of an unqueſtionable Valour too; yet it is prudence in him to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50841:7"/>call in Strangers, to give Life and a new Vigour to his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies upon occaſion.</p>
            <p>XII. But in our caſe there is another reaſon not to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, why the preſent Government thinks it neceſſary to make uſe of Foreigners for our aſſiſtence, and it is this: That though the Nation be full of ſtout and valiant Men, that might alone doe the buſineſs, yet 'tis to be conſidered in this unparallel'd juncture of our Affairs, that if we divide the three Kingdoms into ſix parts, two I doubt, at leaſt, would prove, either <hi>JACOBITES,</hi> or diſaffected to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Government: Now what if the King raiſed an Army, conſiſting in part of <hi>Jacobites,</hi> or of Perſons diſaffected to the preſent Government, ſince 'tis hard to know the bottom of Men's Hearts, what if, I ſay, this hapned, might not ſuch an accident as this, not altogether impoſſible, endanger the whole Nation, and throw it into the greateſt confuſion imaginable, either by ſetting up King <hi>James</hi> again, and the French Intereſt, or by converting this ancient and moderate Monarchy into a Common-Wealth, which would prove perhaps no leſs the ruine of the Nation, than an Abſolute, Arbitrary, and Tyrannical Government? Is it not then more adviſable now, and I am ſure thoſe that love their Religion, and the preſent Intereſt, will be of my Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, to make uſe in this juncture of Foreigners, together with the Natives, to keep a little in awe the hidden <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobites,</hi> and ſuch as are diſaffected to this Government, leſt they undertake to ruine the Nation, upon the firſt fair op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to execute their treaſonable and pernicious deſigns? This complaint of our Male-Contents had been more plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible in another juncture of time, than in ſuch an one as this is, which once ſucceſsfully over, and a Peace concluded, we are ſecured by our Laws from our own ſtanding Forces, as well as from Foreigners. In the mean time we ought to look to our ſelves, as all Wiſe Men ought to do, and ſecure
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50841:8"/>our ſelves againſt preſſing and preſent dangers the beſt way we can, without minding remoter accidents, and meerly poſſible events, that are not yet ſo much as in proſpect; for upon meer Apprehenſions, and groundleſs Fears, of what is never like to happen, to put a veil before our Eyes, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring us to ſee the brink of the Precipice we now ſtand upon, is an unaccountable piece of Folly, or rather Madneſs, that no Man having his Wits about him can be guilty of; yet we muſt needs prove guilty of ſuch a piece of Madneſs and Folly, if through a groundleſs fear of what can never happen in <hi>England,</hi> as things are now ordered; we ſhould ſcruple to ſecure our ſelves by the help of Foreigners from the <hi>Jaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites,</hi> and the Malecontents who might perhaps get the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per hand, if not prevented in time by ſome good Method as this is now thought to be.</p>
            <p>XIII. No farther incroachments upon our Rights and Privileges are to be feared in time to come, ſince the bad ſucceſs of all our late Kings, is an example to all their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, wherein they may read their Deſtiny, if they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood ſo little their own Intereſt, as to act arbitrarily, as ſome of their Predeceſſors did, to the great diſturbance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed of their Subjects for a time, but at laſt to the utter ruine of Themſelves, and their Adherents: His preſent Majeſty is ſo fully perſuaded of this Truth, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Sovereign's Greatneſs, in <hi>England,</hi> depends chiefly and only upon the love of his Subjects; that taking his Intereſt and the People's to be the ſame, as really it is, and always ought to be, to ſhun the dangerous Factions of Court and Country, he pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently complyed with their juſt deſires, to whatever they thought fit to be done for the common good. I am then of Opinion, that <hi>England</hi> was never ſo happy as 'tis now, [ſaying aſide the conſideration of the preſent War ſo abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary,] becauſe of the good underſtanding of the King and his Subjects, though our Seditious Pamphleteer
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50841:8"/>leaves no Stone unturned to divide them; whoever he is, he muſt needs be a Man of a ſtrangly diſaffected Spirit, ſince he blames the late Parliament for allowing his Majeſty ſo much Power as makes him a true King, and not the hate repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation and ſhadow of One, an be would really be, if according to the project ſuggeſted by this Man, he ſhould not be allowed ſo much as the liberty of chooſing his own Councellors, nor of Proroguing Perliaments either, upon occaſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>XIV. The ſuſpending and ſtopping, or <hi>ſtabbing,</hi> as he calls it, of the <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> Act, puts him in a great fit againſt the late Parliament, as having by this ſuſpenſion wronged the liberty of the Subjects; yet if before we give our laſt judgment upon the matter, we conſider as we ſhould do all things impartially, not ſuffering our ſelves to be byaſſed by a wrong apprehenſion of things, we ſhall eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcover, that the ſuſpending of that Act, at that time, was the only way to ſecure our Properties and Liberties, by preventing a Civil and Domeſtick War, which in all likely hood had enſued, had it not been prevented in time, by impowering the King to ſecure ſuch as, becauſe of their Quality, or their former Engagements with the Papiſts, and with the then Male contents, were likelieſt to prove Ring-leaders to new diſturbances, in a time when things were not as yet ſettled upon ſo ſure a Foundation as they now are.</p>
            <p>XV. But nothing more inſufferable in this Seditious Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phleteer, than his affected jealouſie of his Majeſty's being a ſincere Proteſtant, as if the Nation ſhould be the more affraid of him upon this Account, becauſe for ſooth the Parliament is likelier to give him more Power, than if he were a Papiſt, or of a contrary Religion to that of the Nation: This is ſuch an unaccountable Reflexion, that I cannot but wonder to hear it from the Mouth of any Man, that either pretends to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50841:9"/>ſenſe, or reaſon; for, Firſt, At this rate of arguing, it would be better for us to have a ſting we hated, and feared, than one of the ſame Religion we loved, and were ſure of; which is ſuch an abſord inference, that node but a Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man can propoſe it as reaſonable. Secondly, Grant what he ſays to be true, as it is not, our Religion however is ſecure, and perhaps the ſecurer, the greater Power we truſt him with. But, Thirdly, As our late Repreſentatives gave ſo much Power to our Glorious Deliverer, as made him a King, and a powerful one too; ſo on the other hand, they have had ſo much regard to the ſafety of the People, as to ſecure their Privileges and Civil Rights from any future incroachments of the Prerogative, as may eaſily be made out by the late Act, declaring the Rights and Liberties of the Subject, and ſettling the Succeſſion or the Crown.</p>
            <p>XVI. The Popiſh Subjects are generally ſo oppreſſed by their abſolute Sovereigns, that through an exceſſive flattery, and fear of blows, they ſeem to Worſhip their Kings as Gods, allowing them an illimited Power, which no Man of Senſe can admit of in a Being of a limited Nature, or at leaſt allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to be the Fathers, and abſolute Maſters of their People, though the Kings generally came out of the Peoples Loins, as being at firſt made by them, and not the People out of theirs; and though Subjects ought not to lord it over their Sovereigns, as Maſters, yet they ought not to be their Slaves neither, but are to enjoy under their Government ſuch Privileges and Liberties, as may ſettle them in an unalterable State of Happineſs, that the Princes themſelves may not deſtroy at pleaſure; for as nothing is more rational than that we ſhould ſubmit in all things to the abſolute Power of God over us, ſo nothing is more unreaſonable than a blind obedience to earthly Princes, as if they were as infallible as God himſelf; whereas their very Kingſhip proves ſometimes an occaſion to make them the more liable both to Errour, as being
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50841:9"/>often miſ-informed of things, and to Sin likewiſe, if they are not truly Religious, as King <hi>William</hi> undoubtedly is, becauſe of their uncontrolled Power of doing what they pleaſe.</p>
            <p>XVII. For theſe and other reaſons of that kind, though <hi>William</hi> the Third, whom God long preſerve, be the mildeſt and moderateſt Prince that ever ſate upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Throne, yet our Repreſentatives, to ſecure us from the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments of this, and all ſucceeding Ages, have thought fit to declare and eſtabliſh the Rights of the People, ſo fully, and upon ſuch a ſure Foundation, that <hi>England</hi> now is the ſecureſt, and the happieſt Nation in the World, if the Natives can be but ſenſible of their own Happineſs. <hi>Foelices nimium bona ſi ſua nôrint Agricolas!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>XVIII. Four things eſpecially declared in this Act, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure us from Oppreſſion, Tyranny, and Arbitrary Power. Firſt, The rejecting of either a diſpenſing, or ſuſpending Power. Secondly, All grants of Money for, or to the uſe of the Crown reſerved to the Parliament for the time in being. Thirdly, The disbanding of ſtanding Armies in time of Peace, unleſs the Parliament give conſent to the keeping them on foot. Fourthly, The ſettling of the Succeſſion of the Crown. I need mention nothing elſe contained in this Act, to ſhew that we are the only Subjects in the World, that can boaſt of Freedom and Liberty, in caſe our Princes cannot diſpenſe with our Laws, as they cannot without our leave, ſince they are not to give us, for the only reaſon of their Kingly Actions, <hi>Tel est noſtre bon plaiſir, Their Good Will and Pleaſure,</hi> as the French King does; for however the French Modes have taken with us of late, we could never yet fall in love with ſo abſolute a Mode as this. As our Kings muſt act by Law, and not abſolutely, though real Kings, they do nothing of moment but by and with the advice of their Parliaments: Our Happineſs then conſiſts in this, that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50841:10"/>our Princes are tied up to the Law, as well as we, and upon an eſpecial account obliged to keep it up in its full force; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if they deſtroyed the Law, they deſtroy at the ſame time themſelves, by overthrowing the very Foundation of their Kingly Grandeur, and Regal Power: So that our Government not being Arbitrary, but Legal, not Abſolute, but Political, our Princes can never become Arbitrary, Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute, or Tyrants, without forfeiting at the ſame time their Royal Character, by the breach of the eſſential Conditions of their Regal Power, which are to act according to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Cuſtoms, and ſtanding Laws of the Nation. If we are happy upon this account, that our Kings can neither ſuſpend, nor deſtroy our Laws, we are no leſs to be envyed that our Purſes are ſecured from the encroachments of an aſpiring Covetouſneſs, by that part of this Act, which tells us, <hi>that levying Money for, or to the uſe of the Crown by prerence of Prerogative, without grant of Parliament, for longer time, or in other manner, than the ſame is, or ſhall be granted, is illegal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>XIX. We may eaſily think our Security greater than that of any other Nation in <hi>Europe,</hi> if we reflect but a moment upon this important Article, that we are never obliged to open our Purſes, but by the order and conſent of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives, whom we have truſted with the care of our Intereſt, which being equally theirs at the ſame time, we have no reaſon to fear that they ever lay any Taxes upon us, but when 'tis abſolutely neceſſary for the preſervation of our Lives, Liberties, and Religion, as all ſeeing Men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs it to be, in the preſent juncture of our Affairs, to prevent the return of Popery, and Arbitrary Power. This Privilege has made our Government to be envyed by all the Neighbour Nations, and the happieſt that can be imagined; for there being no ſurer way for a Prince to become Abſolute, Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, and a Tyrant, than to impoveriſh his Subjects, to that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50841:10"/>degree of Want and Miſery, as may force them for ſubſiſtence to comply with all his deſires, whether juſt, or unjuſt, he is diſabled by this Act from doing them any miſchief that way, I mean by ſqueezing the Blood out of their Veins, that is the Money out of their Pockets, for any deſign he might have of ruling over them as meer Slaves: To the want of Privilege, we may chiefly aſcribe the Slavery the French Nation groans under, their Prince diſpoſing abſolutely of their Eſtates at pleaſure, and laying ſuch heavy Taxes upon his Subjects, as leave them not Money enough to buy Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Shoes, inſtead of which they are forced to make uſe of Wooden ones; ſo that the French are not ſo much in the wrong, as one would think, when in their flattering Pane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyricks they ſtyle him ſometimes their God, ſince they in a manner are his Creatures, whom he creates, or deſtroys, by the leaſt Word of his Mouth; for ſo abſolute his Power is, that his Will is the only Law they can depend upon; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that when he publiſheth his Orders for gathering of Money, if his Subjects cannot ſupply him otherways, they muſt ſell their Goods, and whatever they have, to give him what he demands; yea, I have known in <hi>France</hi> poor People ſell their Beds, and lie upon Straw, ſell their Pots, Kettles, and all their neceſſary Houſhold Goods, to content the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merciful Collectors of the King's Taxes. By this little hint we may eaſily ſee how much happier we are, as being laden with noburthens but what we are able to bear, and enjoying ſecurely our Eſtates, and whatever we can call our own, under the protection of our Laws. Should we then leave any Stone unturn'd to keep our ſelves as we are, by oppoſing to our utmoſt ſuch a cruel Conqueror, as the French King would undoubtedly prove, if he ever to our great misfortune ſubdued us?</p>
            <p>XX. But let us ſpeak one Word to the third thing I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned before, that by this Act we are to have no ſtanding
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50841:11"/>Army in time of Peace, the advantage whereof we may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily conceive, if we look a little aſide towards our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours the French; they ſuffer patiently in time of War the heavieſt Taxes, and would not think themſelves ſo much to be pityed, as now they are, if a Peace concluded with the Enemy bettered their condition; for they are then in a worſe conditon, in a manner, than they were before, becauſe the ſtanding Armies impower their Prince to doe what he pleaſes in time of Peace; 'tis then that he looks about him, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider who has got together any conſiderable Treaſures, that he may eaſe them of them, though lawfully gained, and by good ſervices done to the Crown; ſo that it is no wonder if the French Subjects chuſe at any time War, rather than Peace, becauſe in time of Peace, their King's Armies are whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imployed againſt them, whereas in the time of a ſettled War, they are partly taken up in oppoſing a Foreign Enemy. Let the impartial Reader judge from the Premiſes of the Happineſs of the Engliſh Subjects, compared with the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Condition of the French.</p>
            <p>XXI. The late Parliament has done another thing, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which, nothwithſtanding all our other advantages con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in this Act, our Happineſs had not been laſting, as it is now like to be for ever, and it is the ſettling of the Succeſſion of the Crown upon Proteſtants, and none but Proteſtants: The Words of the Act are ſo remarkable, that I think it fit to inſert them here, before I give you my Reflexions upon them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereas it has been found by ſad experience, that it is inconſiſtent with the ſafety of this Proteſtant Kingdom, to be governed by a Popiſh Prince, or by any King, or Queen, Marrying a Papiſt, the ſaid Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, do further pray that it may be
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50841:11"/>enacted That all, and every Perſon, and Perſons, that is, or ſhall be reconciled to, or hold Communion with the See, or Church of</hi> Rome; <hi>or ſhall profeſs the Popiſh Religion, or ſhall Marry a Papiſt, ſhall-be excluded, and be for ever uncapable to Inherit, Poſſeſs, or Enjoy the Crown and Government of this Realm, and</hi> Ireland, <hi>and the Dominions thereunto belonging, or any part of the ſame, or to have, uſe, or exerciſe any Regal Power, Authority, or Juriſdiction within the ſame; and in all, or every ſuch caſe, or caſes, the People of theſe Realms ſhall be, and are hereby abſolved of their Allegiance, and the ſaid Crown, and Government, ſhall from time to time deſcend to, and be enjoyed by ſuch Perſon, or Perſons, being Protestants, as ſhould have inherited, and enjoyed the ſame, in caſe the ſame Perſon, or Perſons, ſo recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled, holding Communion, or Profeſſing, or Marrying as aforeſaid, were naturally dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>XXII. Nothing more certain than what is here aſſerted, that it is inconſiſtent with the ſafety of this Proteſtant King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to be govern'd by a Popiſh Prince, or by any King, or Queen, Marrying a Papiſt: If we look back to the publick Tranſactions in the days of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, we ſhall ſoon be convinced of this undeniable Truth, ſince we may derive all our Domeſtick and Civil Diſturbances from his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying a Popiſh French Princeſs, who at laſt became ſo trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome to him, that he was forced to ſend home, to <hi>France</hi> again, all her Attendants, in hopes to bring her to a better temper, by removing from her ſuch Popiſh Emiſſaries, as were thought to put her upon ſome dangerous deſigns, which
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50841:12"/>made the Nation jealous of her ſecret Intrigues with <hi>France,</hi> yea, and ſometimes of the very King's Religion, as if he had been perverted by the Queen, or her Prieſts, or had ſhown himſelf ſomewhat too much inclined to the Popiſh way of Worſhip; but whether things were juſt as the People fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied them, or not, it is certain this unlucky Match was the occaſion of our Civil Wars, and of ſo much bloodſhed in thee three Nations: Such another ſuſpicion as this, was the ſecret ſpring of all our late Domeſtick Troubles, during the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, for though he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed outwardly the Proteſtant Religion, yet the People, upon what grounds I know not well, could not be ſometimes ſatisfied, but that he was either a Papiſt, or popiſhly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined; and upon this very account the Nation was always apprehenſive of French Penſioners, of Popiſh Plots, of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, and Arbitrary Power: Now ſuch apprehenſions and fears could not but be the ſeed of Diviſions among us, of Heart-burnings, and either of grounded, or groundleſs Jealouſies, to the endangering the Peace and Safety of the whole Kindgom: So true it is, that it is inconſiſtent with the ſafety of this Kingdom to be governed by a Prince thought to be popiſhly affected, but ſure far more to be governed by a ſincere, zealous, and profeſſed Papiſt, as we all know King <hi>James</hi> gloryed to be; how near we were the brink of our ruine during his Reign, and how unavoidable our entire ruine was, had he reigned longer over us, is ſo evident to all ſeeing Men, that I need not enlarge upon the matter here. I ſhall only add in this place, in order to make out the Truth of what is aſſerted by the late Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, <hi>that it is inconſiſtent with the ſafety of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Kingdom to be governed by a Papiſt,</hi> that when our Prince is a real Papiſt, he is obliged by the Principles of his Religion, to doe his utmoſt endeavours to ſubmit his Subjects to the Pope's juriſdiction.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:50841:12"/>
            <p> XXIII. Firſt, Becauſe he muſt then of courſe look upon his Subjects as real Hereticks, and Schiſmaticks, whom if he do not root out by all poſſible means, he is liable to be depoſed by the Pope, according to the famous and known deciſion of the third Council of <hi>Lateran;</hi> How then can a Proteſtant Nation put any truſt in ſuch a Prince, whoſe whole buſineſs is, and ought to be, to deſtroy their Religion, and force them to return to the old Romiſh Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions again? And if Subjects cannot truſt their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign, it is but rational to think they will take all ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable meaſures to prevent their own ruine, and that of their Religion, always dearer to them, if they have any Piety at all, than their very lives; but theſe very meaſures, how juſt ſoever, muſt needs breed ſtirs in a Nation, to the general diſturbance of the Natives, ſince the Politick Body, no more than the Natural, can be a moment in a quiet temper, without a free and friendly intercourſe and communication between the Head and the Members. Secondly, If a Popiſh Prince is obliged in Conſcience, as I elſewhere intimated he is, neither to ſtand to his Promiſe, nor Word given, to protect Hereticks, and Hereſie, how can he ſincerely promiſe to maintain and defend our Church; or rather how can we be ſo ſilly as to believe he will maintain it, ſince it is not in his Power to do it, in caſe he finds himſelf in a poſture to undertake its ruine? But, Thirdly, to be ſomewhat more particular, the ſafety of this Nation was inconſiſtent with the Government of the late King <hi>James,</hi> upon a particular account that I ſhall here mention.</p>
            <p>XXIV. Of all the different Perſecutions of the Church of God, none can be compared to the late Perſecution of <hi>France,</hi> both for its Cruelty, and Novelty. The <hi>Roman</hi> Emperors, I confeſs, exerciſed all imaginable Barbarities upon the Bodies of the Primitive Chriſtians, but never
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50841:13"/>attempted, or pretended any right over their Souls, and Conſciences; they baniſhed them, tortured them, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented all ſorts of Death to deſtroy them; but the art of Dragooning Men into Religion, was reſerved to be the contrivance of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Fourteenth, though he was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged by the moſt ſolemn Edicts of <hi>Nants</hi> and <hi>Nime,</hi> and by his Coronation Oath, to protect and defend the French Proteſtants, with all their Rights and Privileges: Had he declared he would ſuffer no longer the <hi>Hugonots</hi> in his Kingdom, and ordered them upon that account to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of it, if they could not change their Religion, we had not complained ſo much of his ſeverity, how An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti-Chriſtian ſoever, but not to ſuffer his Subjects to leave him, nor to live with him, without turning to his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, and that not by Argument, but by all the Wounds the Dragooning Swoord could inflict, that of Death only, which in this caſe was the leaſt, excepted, is ſuch an example of Cruelty, as is not to be parallell'd by the greateſt Fury of the Roman Perſecutions; and which without doubt contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted not a little to our late happy Revolution, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terming the Engliſh through an abſolute neceſſity to do what they did for their own ſafety; for had they not reaſon to look to themſelves, conſidering the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of the French King, contrary to all his Oaths and Promiſes, to maintain, defend, and protect the <hi>Hugo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nots;</hi> they could not but know that the late King <hi>James</hi> was more devoted to the intereſt of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> than <hi>Lewis</hi> the Fourteenth himſelf; ſo that they could not in prudence but take the meaſures they have ſo ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsfully taken, for their own preſervation, and that of the Proteſtant Intereſt in general. In one Word, nothing could be more terrible to the Engliſh, who are ſo much in love with Liberty and Property, than to ſee them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves threatned to be Dragoon'd out of both, by the help
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:50841:13"/>of ſuch a powerfull Allie as <hi>Lewis</hi> the Fourteenth: The late Parliament then conſidering the great progreſs King <hi>James</hi> had made, in a very ſhort time, towards the brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging in of the French Method of converting People to Popery, and what impreſſions ſuch a Precedent as that of <hi>France</hi> might make upon a Prince, that needed no ſpur to the promoting of his own Religion, thought it fit, and abſolutely neceſſary, for the ſafety of the Proteſtant Religion, and the Peace of this Kingdom, to exclude for ever from the Imperial Throne of <hi>England</hi> all Popiſh Princes, whereby not <hi>England</hi> only is ſecured from ſuch Troubles, as always enſue upon any jealouſie between the King and the People from different Principles of Religion, but likewiſe all the Proteſtant Princes abroad, are incouraged to ſtand their ground againſt Popiſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaders, ſince they may be ſure of ſeaſonable ſuccours upon occaſion, from the Proteſtant Princes of this power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Monarchy.</p>
            <p>Though what has been hitherto ſaid, does ſufficiently juſtifie all the proceedings of the King, and late Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to the ſatisfaction of all ſuch as are but impartial Men, and not diſaffected to the preſent Government; yet becauſe ſome Men ſeem diſcontented at two things not done by the late Parliament, and which they think ought not to have been omitted, as being undoubtedly of no ſmall conſequence for the publick Concerns, and Peace of the Nation; it may not be amiſs in this place, to clear all their ſcruples upon theſe two Heads, <hi>viz</hi> Why the late Parliament neither ſettled the Militia of the Kingdom, nor paſſed the Act of Indempnity, though earneſtly preſſed to it by the King, in order to the quieting of Peoples Minds. As to what relates to the ſettling the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia of the Kingdom, it is to be conſidered, that how neceſſary ſoever it may ſeem to be, it was neither perhaps poſſible as
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50841:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:50841:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:50841:15"/>then things ſtood, nor expedient to ſettle it, by reaſon of the uncertain, and unknown diſpoſition of moſt Men's Minds at firſt, in all great and ſudden Revolutions, but more eſpecially in ſuch an extraordinary and unprecedented one as ours was; for ſince our greateſt ſtrength conſiſts in our Militia, can any Man of Senſe think, or ſay, 'twas either fit, or ſecure, in the then poſture of our Affairs, to deliver up the very Bulwark of the Nation, into the Hands of ſuch high Officers, as the Lieutenants of the Militia are in <hi>England,</hi> till it was better known if thoſe who were fit for ſuch Places, were really Men of ſuch a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, as the preſent Government might truſt to, and rely upon: For extraordinary Revolutions of State being much of the Nature of great Waters, toſſed to and fro by boiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Winds, do always require ſome time before they are ſettled again, in ſuch a calm as may encourage both pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Men to follow their former meaſures, and likewiſe thoſe who ſit at the Helm to undertake, and proſecute the fitteſt Methods for ſecuring themſelves, and the People under their Government, from new Dangers and Storms, always to be feared after a ſudden and unexpected Calm, as ours was; we were under ſuch a diſmal Cloud of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent and threatning dangers, a little before the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens cleared up from the Dutch coaſt, that we do won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at this very Day, to ſee our ſelves eſcaped ſuch an unavoidable Shipwreck, as we thought our ſelves then expoſed to; but it is not enough that we are got on Shore, and a <hi>terra firma</hi> to ſtand upon, unleſs by look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nearer into the matter, we conſider ſeriouſly with our ſelves, how to maintain our ground, and ſettle what we have done upon a ſure foundation; for as our late happy Revolution was a real one, how odd ſoever, and unlooked for, ſo conſidering how eaſily Men change their Reſolutions, and becauſe it might be immediately. ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:50841:15"/>by an unhappy one after the like manner, it was a piece of great prudence in our late Repreſentatives, not to be over haſty in ſettling the Militia of the Nation, till both they and the King were throughly acquainted with thoſe who were to be truſted with Commiſſions of ſuch an high concern; but it being impoſſible they ſhould underſtand their real temper, while all things were as yet on float, no wonder if they deferred the ſettling of the Militia, till the Hearts of Men were known to be firſt ſettled, which Time only could inform them of. As to the Act of Indempnity, it is clear there was little or no inconveniency to defer it for a while; for ſince it relates moſtly to ſuch as have been guilty of Irregula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, and Illegal Proceedings in the late Reign, where is the harm if the Government keep them ſomewhat in awe, by deferring their Pardons to more fettled times, leſt they might prove Ringleaders to new Changes, if they were not check'd by the fear of the puniſhment their paſt crimes deſerve? For it is a groundleſs reflexion to ſay, that the not paſſing of the Act of Indempnity encourageth them to doe their utmoſt endeavours to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the bringing in of King <hi>James</hi> again, ſince it is clear to all Men acquainted with the preſent poſture of his Majeſty's Affairs, both at home and abroad, that they muſt needs deſpair of ever being ſecure, if they hope for no ſecurity till King <hi>James</hi> is ſettled upon his Abdicated Throne again: And may not I be allowed to ſay, that to judge of things to come, by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent temper of the Nation, they are in no danger at all, or at leaſt not ſo great as ſome would have them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend it to be, becauſe of the great moderation the Government has hitherto ſhewn, and will undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew hereafter, to all ſuch as are willing to comply with the preſent, that is the Proteſtant Intereſt, in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50841:16"/>oppoſition to Popery, and the French King's Deſigns againſt our Properties, and Liberties, if by the help of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts, and other Male-Contents, he were enabled to conquer us. But to mention here another preſſing particular relating to this Subject, ſince it is well known, that at the ſitting down of the late Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, the King, by the advice, yea, and earneſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt too of our late Repreſentatives, entered into a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary War againſt <hi>France</hi> on the one hand, and againſt the Iriſh Papiſts in <hi>Ireland</hi> on the other hand, I would fain know from any not deſigning Man, what was fitteſt to be done in this caſe, was the time to be trifled away with the ſettling of the Militia, and paſſing an Act of Indempnity, before any ſupplies had been granted his Majeſty, for maintaining this Kingdom, and his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, againſt the formidable French King's Fleets at Sea, and his Iriſh Forces at Land, commanded by the late King <hi>James</hi> in <hi>Ireland?</hi> Sure all Men of Senſe muſt needs confeſs, that this <hi>Principal</hi> was firſt to be minded before any ſuch <hi>Acceſſories,</hi> as undoubtedly theſe were, in that juncture of our Affairs. Now it is methinks evident, that the ordering the Sinews of great Warlike Preparations both by Sea, and by Land then, as now ſo neceſſary, could not but take up a great deal of time, eſpecially when the Money is to be levyed, in due pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, upon all the chief Subjects of the Nation; the neceſſary debates upon ſuch occaſions, about the Summ it ſelf to be raiſed, upon what, and the manner how it is to be gathered, are things of ſuch a Nature, as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be done on a ſudden, whatever Men's endeavours may be to bring them in a ſhort time to a period. The late Tranſactions of the laſt Parliament, beſides the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the thing it ſelf, are evident proofs of what I do here affirm, to all ſuch as underſtand any thing in Affairs
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:50841:16"/>of this kind, never done in <hi>England,</hi> otherwiſe than by Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Conferences, Committees, Debates, Votes, and ſuch other like Methods uſed in Parliament, upon all matters of a General, and National Concern. To conclude, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all that I have ſaid, grant it was expedient, though I have ſufficiently proved it was not, to ſettle the Militia of the Kingdom, and paſs the Act of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempnity, before any thing elſe; theſe ſo much talked of omiſſions, are both inconſiderable in themſelves, ſince we ſmart not yet for them, and not at all dangerous in their Conſequences, which if really hurtful, may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be prevented by the next Parliament.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:50841:17"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>Dorman Newman,</hi> at the <hi>King's-Arms</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Hiſtory of the Treaty at <hi>Nimeguen;</hi> with Remarks on the Intereſt of <hi>Europe,</hi> in relation to that Affair. Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated out of <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Vindication of the preſent great Revolution in <hi>England;</hi> in five Letters paſſed betwixt <hi>James Welwood,</hi> M. D. and Mr. <hi>John March,</hi> Vicar of <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> upon <hi>Tyne.</hi> Occaſioned by a Sermon Preached by him on <hi>Jan.</hi> 30. 1688/9. before the Mayor and Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, for <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> and <hi>Non-Reſiſtance.</hi> The ſecond Edition.</p>
            <p>An Anſwer to the late King <hi>James's</hi> Declaration, dated at <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi>-Caſtle, the <hi>8th.</hi> of <hi>May</hi> laſt, To all his pretended Subjects of the Kingdom of <hi>England:</hi> And ordered by the Vote of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> to be burnt by the common Hang-man.</p>
            <p>A Seaſonable Diſcourſe, wherein is examined what is Lawful during the Confuſions and Revolutions of Government; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the Caſe of a King deſerting his Kingdoms: And how far a Man may lawfully conform to the Powers and Commands of thoſe who with various ſucceſſes hold Kingdoms. Whether it be Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, 1. In Paying Taxes. 2. In Perſonal Service. 3. In Taking Oaths. 4. In giving himſelf up to a final Allegiance. As alſo whether the Nature of War be inconſiſtent with Nature of the Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtory of the Plot Anatomized: Or, the late Sham-Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical-Plot briefly and plainly laid open, wherein thoſe Worthy Patriots who were charged therewith are vindicated, from the Malicious and Falſe Aſperſions caſt upon them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Murmurers, A Poem: To which is added the Character of a Grumbletonian.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joannis Georgii Graevii Oratio de Auſpicatiſſima Expeditione Britan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica, cum Potentiſſimus &amp; Invictiſſimus Guilielmus Arauſionenſis Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps, Angliae, Galliae, &amp; Hiberniae Rex inauguraretur, Die xj. Aprilis; Auctoritate Praepotenſium &amp; Illuſtrium Ordinum Trajectinae Dioeceſeos habita</hi> 1689.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:50841:17"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Ad Auguſtiſſimum Magne Britannia, Frenciae, Hiberniaeque, Regem, Guilielmum <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na cum Maria Aug. conſecratum <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>/22 April. AE. Vulg.</hi> 1689. <hi>Adlocutio, Qua pro Imperii Aeternitate &amp; Salute Regnorum vota nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupat Fridericus Spanhemius, F. F.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reaſons why the Parliament of <hi>Scotland</hi> cannot comply with the late King <hi>James</hi>'s Proclamation, ſent lately to that Kingdom, and proſecuted by the late Viſcount <hi>Dundee.</hi> Containing an Anſwer to every Paragraph of the ſaid Proclamation; and vindicating the ſaid Parliament their preſent Proceedings againſt Him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Noſce Teipſum:</hi> Or, A Leading-ſtep to the Knowledge of our Selves, as the ſureſt Foundation to true Religion in all Perſuaſions. In a brief Diſcourſe of Man's being made and undone, in order to his more happy Recovery. And alſo of the Original and Nature of Man's Body and Soul; and of the Faculties, or different Ways of the Soul's Operation in the Body. With a brief Diſcourſe of the Lord's Day, and of the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper. By an unworthy (but happy) Proſelite of Religion and Morality. To which is added a Poem, treating of Humane Reaſon, and the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Original, and Immortality of the Soul; written nigh one hundred years ſince, by Sir <hi>John Davies,</hi> Attorney-General to Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and now herewith reprinted.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtory of Self-Defence, in requital to the Hiſtory of Paſſive Obedience.</p>
            <p>The Dilucidator: Or, Reflections upon modern Tranſactions, by way of Letters, from a Perſon at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> to his Friend in <hi>London.</hi> Publiſhed once a Fortnight.</p>
            <p>The Sighs of <hi>France</hi> in Slavery, Firſt, Second, Third, and Fourth Memorials.</p>
            <p>A Breviary of the Hiſtory of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> expreſſed in three Parts: 1. The Cauſes and Beginning of the Civil War of <hi>England.</hi> 2. A ſhort Mention of the Progreſs of that Civil War. 3. A compendious Relation of the Original and Progreſs of the ſecond Civil War. Written by <hi>Thomas May,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>.</p>
            <p>A ſhort view of the Methods made uſe of in <hi>Ireland,</hi> for the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion and Deſtruction of the Proteſtant Religion and Intereſt in that Kingdom, from the beginning of the Reign of the late King <hi>James</hi> to this Time: And of the Suffering of the Proteſtants all along. By a Clergy-Man lately eſcaped from thence.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:50841:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> A brief Expoſition of the Church Catechism, with Proofs from Scripture. By <hi>John Williams,</hi> D. D. Rector of St. <hi>Mildred</hi>'s <hi>Poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey,</hi> and St. <hi>Mary-Cole, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Character of the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> impartially ſet forth in a Letter, in Anſwer to Seven <hi>Quenies;</hi> their Original, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, Intereſt, Loſſes, Preſent Condition, Apprehenſions, and Reſolutions. With Remarks upon the great Charge <hi>England</hi> is like to be at with thoſe People, and the Doſtruction of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom by Famine, if not prevented.</p>
            <p>The Intrigues of the French King at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to Embroil Chriſtendom: Diſcovered in ſeveral Diſpatches paſt betwixt Him and the late <hi>Grand Seignion, Grand Vizcar,</hi> and Count <hi>Teckely.</hi> All of them found among that Count's Papers ſeized in <hi>December</hi> laſt. None of them being hithered ſeen in Engliſh. With ſome Reflexions upon them.</p>
            <p>A Vindication of the two Letters concerning Alterations in the Liturgy, in anſwer to <hi>Vox Cleri,</hi> with an Appendix concerning the Remarks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Hiſtory of <hi>Guſtavu. Adolphus,</hi> ſirnamed the <hi>Great,</hi> King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> with the Life and Reign of his Succeſſor, after <hi>Chriſtina Carolus Guſtavus,</hi> Count <hi>Palatius.</hi> Sold by moſt Bookſellers.</p>
            <p>The Monthly Account of all conſiderable Occurrences, Civil, Eccleſiaſtical, and Military, with all Natural and Philoſophical Productions and Tranſactions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mercurius Reformatus:</hi> Or, The New Obſervator, is continued to be publiſhed every Week.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
